Guide to the Patten Family Papers 1895-1986
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Patten Family Papers
1895-1986
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Patten Family
2339
2.3 linear feet
The Patten Family Papers consists of correspondence; biographical materials; case files; printed materials; school notes and artwork; memorabilia; and photographs. The earlier documents, 1895-1900 primarily pertain to F.E.W. Patten and George Y. Patten. The documents between 1900 and the 1920s generally pertain to George Y. Patten and his first marriage to Eleanor Ferris and their daughter Margaret. The later documents from the 1920s to 1986 refer mainly to George and his second wife, Frances Smith Patten. Letters from Frances Patten while she was in the Middle East as an American Field Staff agent are extensive. George Y. Patten's professional correspondence pertain to such topics as the Montana Automobile Association, the West Gallatin Highway into Yellowstone National Park, and the establishment of a Lewis and Clark Memorial. Printed materials include pamphlets and news clippings on art, Montana history and international travel. School Notes and Records relates entirely to Margaret Patten's secondary school work and shows her interest and endeavors in visual art. Memorabilia refers to Margaret Patten's scrapbook and items collected by Frances Patten. Photographs refer mainly to Frances Smith Patten's Extension Service work and to her marriage to George Y. Patten.
This collection is open for research.
Personal and professional papers and memorabilia created or collected by members of the Patten family were donated to Special Collections on September 29, 1995 by Linda Peavy and Ursula Smith of Middletown Springs, Vermont.
Series 1 Correspondence, 1895-1961
Series 2 Biographical Materials, 1910-1948
Series 3 Subject Files, 1925-1936
Subseries 1 Frances Smith Patten's Extension Service Case Files, 1925-1929
Subseries 2 George Y. Patten's Legal Case Files, 1925-1946
Series 4 Financial Records, 1898-1906
Series 5 Printed Materials, 1921-1986
Series 6 School Notes and Records, 1915-1926
Series 7 Memorabilia, 1911-1940
Series 8 Photographs, 1900-1946
The Patten Family members highlighted in this collection are: Francis England Wall (F.E.W.) Patten (1823-1898); his son George Yager Patten (1876-1951); George's first wife, Eleanor Ferris Patten (d. 1943); their daughter, Margaret Patten (1903- ? ); George's second wife, Sarah Frances Smith Patten (1899-1986).
Born in Missouri, F.E.W. Patten settled in Virginia City, Montana as a merchant in 1863, served in the fourth Montana Territorial Legislature, and until his death in 1898, sold real estate and insurance in Butte. F.E.W. married Mary Amelia Armstrong. Their son, George Y. Patten, was born at Virginia City in 1876 and attended public schools in Butte. After 1893, he worked as a court stenographer and studied law. In 1900, rather than going to law school, George took the bar exam and passed with highest honors. He built up a private practice dealing primarily with corporate law, working closely with the law firm of Cotter and McHatton, and became widely recognized as an expert in mining, water rights, and public policy laws. In 1901, he married Eleanor Ferris (? - 1943), daughter of Colonel Edward and Margaret Eastman Ferris. George and Eleanor had three children, Margaret (1903 - ?), Mary (1905 - ?), and Eleanor Jr. (1913 - ?). George married Sarah Frances Smith in 1945. Frances was born in 1899 in Durham, Kansas. She completed her B.A. in home economics at Kansas State University in 1922, and her M.A. in adult education at Columbia University in 1938. She worked for Kansas State College for the Extension Division from 1925 to 1927. She continued her Extension Service work in Flathead County, Montana until 1929. Frances Patten taught for the Department of Home Economics at Montana State College, Bozeman between 1946 and 1964. She spent the last 7 years of her teaching career doing extension work in the Middle East. George Y. Patten died in Bozeman in 1951. Frances Patten died in Bozeman in 1986.
The Patten Family Papers contain: correspondence; biographical materials; case files; printed materials; school notes and artwork; memorabilia; and photographs. Series are arranged according to document type and files are generally arranged chronologically within each series. The earlier documents, 1895-1900 primarily pertain to F.E.W. Patten and George Y. Patten. The documents between 1900 and the 1920s generally pertain to George Y. Patten and his first marriage to Eleanor Ferris and their daughter Margaret. The later documents from the 1920s to 1986 refer mainly to George and his second wife, Frances Smith Patten. Correspondence contains the personal correspondence of F.E.W. and Mary Patten, and George and Frances Patten. Letters from Frances Patten while she was in the Middle East as an American Field Staff agent are extensive. George Y. Patten's professional correspondence is organized within his case files and pertain to such topics as the Montana Automobile Association, the West Gallatin Highway into Yellowstone National Park, and the establishment of a Lewis and Clark Memorial. Correspondents in these files include Senator Burton K. Wheeler, Horace Albright, and Oscar O. Mueller. Biographical Materials holds news clippings, George Y. Patten's early scrapbook, and Eleanor Ferris Patten's description of her childhood in the American West. Subject Files have been divided into two subseries: One contains Frances Smith Patten's case files, the other contains portions of George Y. Patten's legal case files. Printed materials include pamphlets and news clippings on art, Montana history and international travel. School Notes and Records relates entirely to Margaret Patten's secondary school work and shows her interest and endeavors in visual art. Memorabilia refers to Margaret Patten's scrapbook and items collected by Frances Patten. Photographs refer mainly to Frances Smith Patten's Extension Service work and to her marriage to George Y. Patten. Earlier photographs of the Patten family are found in George Y. Patten's and Margaret Patten's scrapbooks and are filed in the Biographical Materials and Memorabilia series respectively.
Albright, Horace M. (Horace Marden), 1890-1987-Correspondence; Mueller, Oscar O., 1877-1964-Correspondence; Wheeler, Burton K. (Burton Kendall), 1882-1975-Correspondence; Patten, Eleanor Ferris, d. 1943; Patten, F. E. W. (Francis England Wall), 1823-1898; Patten, Frances Smith, 1899-1986; Patten, George Y. (George Yager), 1876-1951; Patten, Margaret, b. 1903; Patten, Mary
Montana Automobile Association; Montana Extension Service in Agriculture and Home Economics; Lewis and Clark Expedition (1804-1806)
Patton family
West Gallatin Highway; Yellowstone National Park
Americans-Middle East-Correspondence; Home economics extension work-Kansas; Home economics extension work-Middle East; Home economics extension work-Montana; Practice of law-Montana; Roads-Montana; Home economics extension workers; Lawyers-Montana
Agriculture; Civil Procedure and Courts; Colleges and Universities; Elementary and Secondary Education; Expeditions and Adventure; Montana; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Case files; Family papers-Montana; Photographs; School notebooks-Montana; Scrapbooks--Montana
- Correspondence, 1895-1961; 1
  Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing letters from members of the Patten family and are arranged chronologically. Early correspondence, prior to 1900, refer to F.E.W. Patten's life and death. The later correspondence contains Frances Patten's letters to Julia Martin, George Y. Patten's cousin, and describe Frances' experiences in the Middle East as an American Field Staff agent, 1956-1964. The majority of George Y. Patten's correspondence are integral to his legal work and are arranged within his case files in the Subject Files series.
  - 1895-1908 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - 1939, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5-12)
- Biographical Materials, 1892-1910; 2
  Biographical Materials contains newspaper clippings, George Patten's scrapbook of his family life at the turn of the century, and a short pioneering account by Eleanor Ferris Patten telling of her early childhood in the American West. George Y. Patten's scrapbook contains both news clippings and photographs from 1892-1910. All other photographs are in Series 8, Photographs.
  - News clippings on Frances Patten (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - News clippings on George Y. Patten (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook complied by George Y. Patten (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pioneering account written by Eleanor Ferris Patten (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Subject Files, 1925-1946; 3
  Subject files contain Frances Smith Patten's extension work case files from 1925 to 1929 and portions of George Y. Patten's legal case files from the 1920s to 1949. The Subject Files series has been divided into two subseries according to creator. Subseries 1 contains Frances Patten's case files, and Subseries 2 contains George Y. Patten's files.
  - Frances Smith Patten's Extension Case Files, 1925-1929; 1
    Frances Smith Patten's Extension Work files are the yearly reports she wrote documenting her work in either Kansas or Flathead County, Montana. They contain information on 4-H clubs, women's/girls' clubs, home economics displays at fairs, women's camps, and clothing design and costs. Photographs have been removed from the files, assigned numbers 7 through 84, and have been placed in Series 8, Photographs. Each removal number has been labeled on its original case file page.
    - Kansas State College--Extension Division Annual Report, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Kansas State College--Extension Division Annual Report, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Montana Extension Service, Flathead County Annual Report, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Montana Extension Service, Flathead County Annual Report, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Montana Extension Service, Flathead County Annual Report, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - George Y. Patten's Case Files, 1925-1946; 2
    Portions of George Y. Patten's legal case files have been separated according to both document type and subject and have been arranged within each subject category chronologically. Files 1-31 refer to his work regarding Montana's highways; files 32-36 contain; files pertaining to the Montana Automobile Association and refer to gasoline taxes and federal funds for road construction, files 37-43 refer to the establishment of a Lewis and Clark Memorial and its proposed location at Bozeman, Montana. File 44, Patten's correspondence with Oscar O. Mueller, involves questions on Montana history. The files 1-31 pertaining to Montana's highways has been subdivided according to specific highways or projects. Files 1-18 refer almost solely to the construction and up keep of the West Gallatin Highway into Yellowstone National Park. Files 19-22 generally contain information on the Bridger Canyon Highway, and files 23-31 generally hold information on Highway 10 and other miscellaneous road projects. There is some overlap in subject materials.
    - Correspondence with Yellowstone Superintendent, Horace Albright, 1925 May-1928 July (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Yellowstone Superintendent, H. Albright, 1928 October-1929 June (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with C. M. & St. P. Railway Co., 1927 March-1928 November (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with C. M. & St. P. Railway Co., 1930 May-1931 April (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with Forest Service, 1925 October-1930 June (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with Congressman Scott Leavitt, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence with State of Montana Highway Commission, 1926 March-1928 May (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with Yellowstone Superintendent, Edmund B. Rogers, 1946 March-1949 July (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence with Yellowstone Superintendent Roger W. Toll, 1930 June-1933 December (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with Senator Thomas J. Walsh, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Conference Memorandum: H. Albright & Bozeman Chamber of Commerce, 1925 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Memorandum, Re: West Gallatin & Gallatin Soldier Station & West Yellowstone Road, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Location Survey Report of West Gallatin Project, Big Horn Pass Section, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Expenditures: West Gallatin Road, 1921-1924 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Committee on West Gallatin Road Petition & Notes, Re: Expenditures, 1926 March (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Yellowstone Comparative Travel Figures, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Press Releases: Yellowstone Park Travel, 1930-1931, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Map: "Proposed Adjustments in Boundaries of Yellowstone National Park" (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence with Good Roads Committee Members. Correspondence with State of Montana Highway Commission, 1932 March 20, 1928 July-1929 December (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence with Senator J.W. Speer, 1932 March (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - News clippings Re: Bridger Canyon Road, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence with Director of National Park Service, Horace Albright, 1930 April-1931 February (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence with Chamber of Commerce, Re: Highway Constructions, 1929 September-December (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence with State of Montana Highway Commission, 1929 August-1933 November (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Joint County Committee Gallatin County Petitions, Re: Bill no. 31, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Leaflet: "The State Highway Treasury Anticipation Debenture Act of 1931" (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Memorandum on County Roads, circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - News clippings, Re: Gallatin County Development Association, 1932 April (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Right of Way Map, Rocky Canyon & Map of Gallatin County, Montana, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence with Montana Automobile Association, 1928 February-March 1930 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence with Montana Automobile Association, Re: Amendments to Revised Codes of Montana 1921, 1928 November-1929 January (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Montana Automobile Association: Annual Meeting Minutes & reports, 1927 November-January 1930 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Montana Automobile Association: Notices to Directors, 1929 April-February 1930 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Montana Automobile Association: Financial Reports, 1929 January-February 1930 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Montana Automobile Association: Audit & Leaflets, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence with Judge Callaway, Re: Lewis & Clark Memorial, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence with Senator Burton K. Wheeler, Re: Lewis & Clark Memorial, 1928 February-1930 May (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Council Joint Memorial Congressional Petitions, 1870s (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Resolution, Re: Lewis & Clark Memorial, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Lewis & Clark Memorial Monument Suggestions by George D. Pease (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Propositions, Re: Locating Lewis & Clark Memorial in Bozeman, Montana (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - News clippings, Re: Lewis & Clark Memorial, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Misc. Correspondence with Oscar O. Mueller, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Standards for Title Opinions" (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "The World Court" (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Financial Records, 1898-1906; 4
  Financial Records contains George Y. Patten's early family and business financial registers.
  - Expenditure Listings, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Household and Business Ledger (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Printed Materials, 1921-1986; 5
  Printed materials include published works and documents collected by Margaret and Frances Smith Patten. Pamphlets refer to art, art exhibitions, Montana history, and Extension Service work. News clippings from the 1970s focus on Frances Patten's continued interest in world travel, and Montana life and communities. Printed materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Pamphlets from New York Art Exhibits, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "A Century of Progress Exhibition of Paintings and Sculpture, June 1 to November 1, 1933" (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Clippings & Pamphlets 1933 World's Fair Art Exhibition (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Finnish Home Economics Pamphlets, 1937, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Recital Program, Montana State College, 1949 September 19 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "American University Field Staff" Reports for Southwest Asia, 1956, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Misc. Pamphlets & Travel Brochures (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Job Corps Conservation Centers Program" Booklet, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Frances Patten's News clippings on Early Montana (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Frances Patten's News clippings on Travel, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Frances Patten's News clippings on Travel, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Frances Patten's News clippings, Misc., 1970s (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Wardrobe Guide Sheet (Box 3, Folder 15)
- School Notes and Records, 1915-1926; 6
  School Notes are arranged chronologically and contain Margaret Patten's secondary and post-school work. Her written works and 1920-1921 school annual are in box 4. Her artwork, found in box 5, contains art exercises in pencil, ink, watercolor, and acrylic. Finished works are found in Box 5, file 2.
  - Report on National Parks, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Report on Washington Irving, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Report on Harriet Beecher Stowe, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Report on Sir Launfal, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Art History Notebook, circa 1915 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Annual of the Cathedral School of St. Mary's, 1920-1921 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - English Notebook, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - History of Art Notebook, circa 1921 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Superficial Anatomy Notebook (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Project on Lamps and Candles, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pencil Sketches (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Paintings & Design Work: Watercolor & Acrylic (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Perspective Notes & Exercises (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Perspective Drawings: Ink & Pencil (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Junior Year, Design Sketchbook: Ink (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Junior Year, Paintings: Watercolor (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Pattern/Design Work: Acrylic & Pencil (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Watercolor Portrait by Jena Easkman (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Magazine Clippings, 1923-1924 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Memorabilia, 1911-1940; 7
  Memorabilia contains objects, some photos and documents collected by either Margaret or Frances Patten. Margaret Patten's scrapbook dates from 1911-1920 and relates her interests and social activities during this time. Frances Patten's memorabilia are limited and contain primarily placecards from and invitations to social gatherings.
  - Margaret Patten's Scrapbook, 1911-1920 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Frances Patten's Place Cards & Invitations (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Frances Patten's Misc. Notations & Fragments (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1900-1946; 8
  All photographs are printed in black and white, and the majority pertain to Frances Patten's work as a home economics instructor for Extension Services and for the Department of Home Economics at Montana State College. Photos in folders 8-12 were removed from the case files in Series 3, subseries 1, and bear the same number indicated on the pages from which they were removed. Frances Patten's marriage to George Y. Patten and subsequent family life is also documented. Missing are any photos of her work in the Middle East. Photographs which were glued to scrapbook pages, and which could not be removed without damage remain in George Y. Patten's scrapbook in box 1, file 15, and in Margaret Patten's scrapbook in Box 6, file 1.
  Photos are arranged chronologically.
  - Eleanor F. Patten's niece, #1, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Cary," #2, circa 1921 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - George Y. Patten, #3, circa 1922 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Margaret Patten's School Photos, #4-6 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Frances Smith Patten's Extension Work Photos, #7, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Francis Smith Patten's Extension Work Photos, #8-12, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - #13-27, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - #28-62, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - #63-84, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Picture Postcards: New York, #85-86 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - George & Frances Patten's Wedding Photos, #87-89, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Family Photos, #90-97, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Frances Patten's MSC Home Economics Department Photos, #98-111, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Professional Copies of Photos at Glacier Park, #112-114 (Box 6, Folder 17)